<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A preservative against atheism and error wherein some fundamental points in religion ... are by way of question and answer handled, and with much brevity and clearness proved ... : to which is added a brief answer to William Russel in a book of his entituled No seventh-day-Sabbath in Christs New Testament / by W. Saller.</title>
            <author>Saller, William, d. ca. 1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S399</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37201</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16268103</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16268103</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105197</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60369)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105197)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1156:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A preservative against atheism and error wherein some fundamental points in religion ... are by way of question and answer handled, and with much brevity and clearness proved ... : to which is added a brief answer to William Russel in a book of his entituled No seventh-day-Sabbath in Christs New Testament / by W. Saller.</title>
                  <author>Saller, William, d. ca. 1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>25, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, stained, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Russel, William, d. 1702. --  No seventh-day-Sabbath in Christs New Testament.</term>
               <term>Christianity --  Essence, genius, nature.</term>
               <term>Atheism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105197:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PRESERVATIVE AGAINST Atheiſm and Error.</p>
            <p>Wherein ſome Fundamental Points in Religion; <hi>VIZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The Eſſence, or Being, of GOD.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Divine Authority of the holy Scriptures.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>The Majeſty, Worth, Uſe, and Perpetuity of the Moral Law, or Law of ten Commandments.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt being the true Meſſiah.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Are, by way of <hi>Queſtion</hi> and <hi>Anſwer,</hi> handled, and with much brevity and clearneſs proved. To put a ſtop to that Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of <hi>Atheiſm, Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Error,</hi> that runneth in this evil day.</p>
            <p>To which is added, A brief ANSVVER to <hi>William Ruſſel</hi> in a Book of his, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>No Seventh-day-Sabhath in Chriſts New Teſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo, A brief Word to the Diſpute in <hi>Stone Chappel</hi> at <hi>Pauls, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By W. SALLER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105197:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105197:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS <hi>Ignorance, Atheiſm,</hi> and <hi>Prophaneſs</hi> hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes abounded in the World, ſo never more than at this day; and not only ſo, but even amongst the zealous and well meaning People of this Nation, there have been all ſubtile endeavours uſed, as far as the temper of the People could bear it, to wheel them round about to the Gates of <hi>Rome</hi> again. And theſe endeavours have not been without great ſucceſs, even in the Churches of Chriſt, corrupting their Principles, and wounding the very heart of Religion amongst ſome of them. And beſides this mortal growing diſeaſe, there is a notorious careleſneſs in the moſt, of preſerving the Grounds of Religion in purity, either by preaching or catechiſing, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as there is ground to fear our diſtempers will grow paſt remedy, unleſs God, by ſome gracious means or other, put a ſtop to that Currant of <hi>Errour,</hi> which through the <hi>Atheiſm</hi> of ſome, and <hi>Ignorance</hi> of others, is let out, and runneth with a mighty ſtream: the ſence whereof hath engaged me to write theſe following lines, which I entreat thee to read and conſider. And if thou beeſt not fully ſatisfied in every point, if I may know the reaſon thereof in word or writing, or in any ſuch way
<pb facs="tcp:105197:3"/>as becomes a perſon fearing God and conſcientiouſly willing to finde out the Truth in Love; I ſhall do the beſt I can to ſatisfie thee. But if I ſhould be fallen upon by ſome railing Scorner, or one whoſe Confidence out-runs his Underſtanding, and all ſober mens alſo, it is like I may take little notice of him. So commending my Lines to thy conſideration, and my prayers to the Lord for thy profiting; as alſo deſiring a ſhare in thine, if thou beeſt one that uſeſt to call upon his Name,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I reſt, <hi>Thy Friend and Servant in the Work of CHRIST, </hi>W. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105197:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Preſervative againſt</hi> ATHEISM <hi>and</hi> ERROUR.</head>
            <p>Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVHat do you judge is the needful work of the day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The day calls for many needful works, and amongſt the reſt, this for one, The laying down ſuch foundations and principles of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Godlineſs, as may through God's bleſſing, recover Religion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to its antient Purity, and preſerve it therein.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What do you think of the many Catechiſms that have been imployed in this ſervice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Many have done worthily in opening he Commandments of God, and in ſhewing the uſe of Chriſt's Ordinances; and ſeveral parts of Truth have been uſefully opened: but yet through their not knowing, or not conſidering, how the world is over-ſpread, partly with Atheiſm, and partly with Ignorance, have miſſed of that which is the main, and ſaid little, or nothing, to that which is of moſt concernment.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What are thoſe weighty Truths, or ſome of them, that ſhould be further ſpoken to?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This for one, namely, The undoubted and unqueſtionable Being of a God.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Do you judge that needful?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea: for it is not ſo long ſince Atheiſm appeared with an open face in the <hi>Ranters;</hi> and how it appears in the lives of multitudes, is too manifeſt. For how do men at this day, ſwear <hi>for</hi> or <hi>againſt</hi> any thing that ſtands with their preſent advantage, and laugh at that in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate as ſuperſtitious and ridiculous, which they in publick ſubſcribe to, as if it were good and ſutable to the mind of God; with many like Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, which men could never conſtantly run on in the courſe of doing, if they did from the heart believe that there is a God: For what is more inconſiſtent with the Being of a God, than to own and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſuch works of Iniquity?</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How will you prove convincingly there is a God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, It is proved by the Creation of the World: for it is altogether impoſſible for the viſible Creation to give it ſelf a being; I mean there is no thing which the eye of man can behold, which could
<pb facs="tcp:105197:4"/>poſſibly give it ſelf a being; muchleſs could it give a being to any thing leſe. As for example, Where can any Man find a creature in heaven or in earth, indued with Reaſon and Underſtanding, and ſo accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with Skill, to bring to paſs ſuch excellent works as he himſelf can do, and yet could he not make himſelf. But it is evident to reaſon, that the firſt of mankind muſt have their Being from God: muchleſs could Man have ſtretched out his hand to the Heavens, and have ſet them at ſuch a wonderful diſtance from the Earth, and have ſtretched them round about it, and ſo beſpangled it with Stars, and have given a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Sun &amp; Moon, and have commanded them to keep their courſe to all Generations: neither could he have made the Earth and the Seas, and have ſtocked them with ſuch variety of Creatures, and bound them in a round lump together, and commanded this bulkie maſſie piece to ſtand firm in the midſt of the Heavens: theſe and ſuch-like Works are too wonderful for any, but only for Himſelf, who is in Mercy, Power, Wiſdom, Fore-knowledge, and all eternal Excellency, Matchleſs and Infinite.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But may it not be objected by an Atheiſt, that all things are by Nature?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It may, and is ſo objected commonly; but the anſwer is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy at hand, thus; If it ſhould be ſuppoſed that all things are by Nature, yet then of neceſſity this cannot be denied, that Nature muſt be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed with ſuch an Almighty Power, unſearchable Wiſdom, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Love to the whole Earth, and eſpecially to Mankind, together with all thoſe moſt glorious Perfections which we commonly aſcribe to God: for moſt evident it is, that He that wrought out the Being, and Well-being of all things, is moſt <hi>richly</hi> furniſhed with the very high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Perfections of all Excellency and Goodneſs; and this is no leſs than to confeſs the Being of a God.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Have you any other proof that there is a God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The works of Providence do further evidence the Being of a God; as firſt, The conſtant Preſervation of the whole Creation, that all the hoſts of Men and Beaſts, Fowls, and all living Creatures, ſhould be in a conſtant courſe of Providence fed every day for thouſands of years together; it evidently ſhews the Fatherly-care, Faithfulneſs, Wiſdom and Bounty of a God.</p>
            <p>Again, if God doth alter his wonted courſe at any time, and make the Heavens Braſs, and the Earth Iron, or bring other ſevere judgements; every conſidering man may clearly diſcern, that the abounding Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe of the Sons of Men, have provoked the Giver of all Goodneſs to take his Mercy away, and may well read in all his ſtroaks, a loud call
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105197:4"/>to repentance. But further, if men do but humble themſelves under his hand, and return from their evil wayes, how graciouſly doth he return to his ordinary way of ſhewing Mercy.</p>
            <p>Alſo, if we do conſider his governing the World, it moſt wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declares his infinite and eternal Being. Take theſe inſtances, firſt, the Sun, Moon and Stats, keeping ſo conſtant a courſe ordinarily from Age to Age: as alſo Day and Night; Summer and Winter; Seed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time and Harveſt, following each other in a ſetled courſe. And if the Lord at any time alter the courſe of any of his Creatures; as when the Sun and Moon ſtood ſtill in <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s dayes, and came back in <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s dayes ten degrees; the Red-ſea divided in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s dayes, and the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of <hi>Jordan</hi> driven back, or any like act done, it alwayes was brought to paſs at ſuch times, and for ſome ſuch noble ends, as that it did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way more abundantly preach forth the <hi>Power, Grace, Wiſdom, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>unſpeakable Goodneſs</hi> of an Eternal God.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But how know you that theſe wonderful Works were done?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Manifeſt it is, that in no age, no not in this we now live in, can any of the great Works of God get any credit in the world, till they are manifeſt beyond all poſſibility of diſpute: therefore there can be no ground for a doubt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider his Strength, Wiſdom and Goodneſs, in governing the World, ſo as that his poor People live in it. It is moſt manifeſt to all that do conſider it, that of them that love and fear God, and are the moſt conſcionable in minding and obſerving his Word, Works and Worſhip, that they are very few, few, few, in compariſon of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, numberleſs multitudes of blaſphemous-Atheiſts, Idolaters, prophane, unjuſt, deceitful Covenant-breakers, with other like workers of Iniquity! all ſetting themſelves with open mouth to devour this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Remnant, and diging to Hell for deep Counſels to deſtroy them; and yet for all their unjuſt and cunning policies, and oft-times open violence exerciſed againſt them, through the rich Goodneſs, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom and Providence of God, they have never yet been root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the Earth; but although they have been almoſt blotted out with the rage and perſecution of the World, yet hath the Moſt High ſtill preſerved a little Flock of Lambs amidſt a world of wolves, who fain would, but never yet could, wholly devour them: which plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proves that there is a God that hath more <hi>Power, Wiſdom</hi> &amp; <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> than all their Enemies have ſtrength or malice, who ever lives to take care of them.</p>
            <p>Again, the Signs that God often ſheweth in the ſudden and unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted overturning of their Enemies from time to time, is of a very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105197:5"/>nature, to prove that certainly there is a God that judgeth the Earth.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Seeing you have proved the undoubted and certain Being of a God, what is the next weighty Truth that ſtands in need of proof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The next Truth moſt needful to be cleared, is the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to be the Words and Counſels of God.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Is there any with us do deny them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, there is ſome do deny them; and more would, if fear or ſhame did not ſtop their mouths, as appears by their works.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What Books do you mean by holy Scriptures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Writings of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, till <hi>Malachies</hi> dayes, committed to the antient Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and received by them: as alſo the Books of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> from <hi>Matthew</hi> to the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>And wherefore do you reject thoſe Books commonly called Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha? do you think the Spirit of God had no hand in the writing of them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It ſeems too hard to conclude, that thoſe that wrote thoſe ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, had no Light or aid from the Spirit of God in the writing of them; they might be good men, and hand forth ſome truths, and uſeful things, as many doubtleſs have done both in former and latter Ages, who, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we may make good uſe of their Books, yet may we not receive them as infallible Prophets writings, but receive, or reject, or ſuſpend our judgements, as we ſee they agree or diſagree with the Word of Truth and clear Reaſon, or appear doubtful.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But is there reaſon to take this liberty with thoſe Books; what are your grounds to doubt of their infallability?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Clear it is, that however there are good Counſels in ſome of thoſe Writings, yet they ſeem to be written by ſome <hi>Jews</hi> in or after the captivity, when their light in all probability was much dimmed, and not by the Prophets: Alſo how far from the language and ſtile of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Spirit of God, thoſe Writings are (ſome of them) is evident: the Spirit of God uſeth not to acknowledge infirmity, and a doing as well as he can, for he is perfect, and therefore doth nothing meanly. Again, as there be abſurdities not fit to be put upon the holy Spirit (as this for one, to go about to make us believe the Devil will be frighted away with ſmoak) ſo alſo there is one ſtark <hi>lie,</hi> ſo rank that a fool may diſcern it; the ſame perſon that ſaith in one place, he is the Son of <hi>Ananias,</hi> ſaith in another, he is an holy <hi>Angel.</hi> There be other exceptions I will not now ſpend time about; theſe may ſuffice to let you ſee ſome ground wherefore I cannot own them to be of divine Authority.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But how will you prove that thoſe books, known by the names of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105197:5"/>Old and New Teſtaments, are the infallible Words of God, and ſo the ſafe Rule to lead men in the true Path of believing and obedience to Life everlaſting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, They may be known by their noble ſtile; as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, When you hear any perſons expreſs themſelves judiciouſly, acute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in excellent Language, although you never ſaw them before, yet may you ſafely conclude that they are perſons of excellent breeding and quality, although they ſhould appear in never ſo mean a dreſs: So may it much more be concluded concerning the Scriptures; their dialect hath that Majeſty, Holineſs, Grace and high Wiſdom in them, moſt elegantly manifeſting the perfections of a divine Being in them, and declaring the judiciouſneſs, faithfulneſs, and perfection of all his Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Proceedings with the ſons of men, that it is not likely poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for any gracious conſidering man, to call there Authority into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The bleſſed Intention and ſcope of them, diſcover them to proceed from the holy Spirit; all the Commandments, Threatnings, Promiſes, Warnings, Counſels &amp; Declarations contained in them, una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly tending to advance Godlineſs in the hearts and lives of men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The ſeveral Doctrines and points of Truth contained in them, are ſo wiſely and holily compacted, ſtanding in ſo ſweet an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on together, and ſo neſſecarily depending one upon another, like the parts and members of a natural body, moſt comely and beautiful, ſo that the higheſt commendations Chriſt gives his Church, in that book of the <hi>Canticles,</hi> doth much more belong to that Body of Divinity held forth in the Scriptures, by which ſhe is begotten and conformed to his Image. Add to this the conſideration of the Pen-men thereof, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Prophets and Apoſtles, and living in ſeveral Ages, yet without jarr have brought forth this noble work; ſo that you may plainly ſee, they were all guided by one and the ſame holy Spirit in the writing of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Effects and lively Power of them in the hearts of men, declare from whence they are deſcended; that which is ſpoken of their ſoul-ſearching and powerful piercing nature, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. every ſoul that ſeriouſly converſeth with them, findeth true: He that in his old blind eſtate took his heart to be good, when he comes to try it by the Scriptures, finds it ſo notoriouſly filthy, that he abhors himſelf; and as it diſcovereth ſin, ſo it purgeth it out, and makes the carnal heart ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, and brings it unto the Love of God and Holineſs, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he hated, and works it up to the hatred of ſin, which before he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; ſo that its transforming nature plainly ſheweth it to be the Words of God.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105197:6"/>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But may not other Books perſwade men as well as that? how many are led by other books into error?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea other books may over-come mens judgements, but not transform their natures, from carnal to be ſpiritual, from earthlymind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs to be heavenly minded, and to bring from the love of ſin to the love of holineſs, as this bleſſed Book of the holy Scriptures doth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The conſtant fulfilling of the Prophecies of them, preach to all men their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nfallibility. God made good his Promiſe to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 15. as alſo that to <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.12. to the 17. Alſo his Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings to <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.2. As alſo the Promiſes made in the 2d of <hi>Haggai,</hi> and 3d of <hi>Malachi,</hi> concerning Chriſt's coming to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Temple, which is now fallen. Alſo Chriſt's Prophecy of the fall of this Temple, and of Jeruſalem, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37, 38. &amp; 24.2, 19, 20, 21, 22. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.20, 21, 22, 23, 24. is alſo come to paſs. As alſo the Prophecy of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. is, you ſee, fulfilled to a tittle, with many more inſtances if need were, all proving their heavenly birth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> The unſupportable burthen of a Conſcience, which God woundeth for ſin; The ſealing Teſtimony of his Love by the Spirit to the ſoul of the true believer; The gracious Anſwers to prayers made to God in the name of Chriſt, with other like experiences, give to all gracious hearts moſt full aſſurance, that the Scriptures were endited by the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly, Jehovah</hi> himſelf hath born witneſs of them, that they are his words beyond all contradiction. 1. By declaring the ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with his own Voice, with that terrour as is expreſt, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. and writing them twice with his own hand; theſe being the grand Law on which the whole Scriptures depend, and being the foundation of all Religion, as by and by will appear. 2. The wonderful Signs and Miracles wrought to confirm them; as the bringing Iſrael out of <hi>Egypt</hi> through the Red-Sea, and the Wilderneſs, and <hi>Jordan,</hi> by a piller of a Cloud by day, and a piller of Fire by night, into <hi>Canaan,</hi> to the terrour of all the Nations round about. Alſo the Sun ſtanding ſtill, and coming back. The Reſurrection of Chriſt, which will be proved anon: and the Reſurrection of others by Chriſt, with other numberleſs Miracles; all preaching to the world, that the Scriptures are the Counſel and Will of God.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But how ſhall we know that theſe wonders have been wrought, but by the Scriptures own Teſtimony, or by the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It may be known if this be conſidered, that the Scriptures have alwayes had, and to this day have, ſo many feigned friends &amp; open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, either flatly oppoſing them, or to their uttermoſt, ſecretly undermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:105197:6"/>and diſgracing them, or exalting humane inventions above them, in ſo much that no ſober Chriſtian can doubt, but that if there had beene poſſibility to have denied the report of thoſe Miracles in that day in which they are ſaid to be done, the World could not have wanted Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes enough to have ſhaken the Faith of the Chriſtian World (ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) long before this day: but although they be carpt at and undermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, yet may all that love them, challenge all their enemies to produce one known and approved Author, that hath undertaken to reprove the report of thoſe glorious Miracles; and if none can be found, then have we the greateſt aſſurance that can be deſired, that they are certainly true.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eightly,</hi> And laſtly, They have a Teſtimony in the conſciences and mouths of thoſe that like not to be ruled by them; and therefore make as little uſe of them as poſſible they can in ſetting up Religion. You have a clear inſtance of the Papiſts, to go no further. Evident it is, that as many Decrees, Canons, Articles, Traditions and Ceremonies, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath, yet with all theſe and her Maſs-book, Pope and Councils to boot, with all their pretended infalliability, yet they cannot have a Religion without the holy Scriptures, although it be a well-known truth that they love them not: For all thoſe that honour and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them, and dare not tranſgreſs thoſe bleſſed Precepts, are the only grand Hereticks with them. And as for ſuch as conform to their abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Idolatries, and ſuperſtitious Inventions, paſs for Catholick peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with them, although they be notorious tranſgreſſors of the Law of God: and yet if theſe men did wholly caſt off the Scriptures, as ill as they love them, their Religion could not have a Being. I am neither inſenſible nor forgetful, that there are both fooliſh &amp; ſubtile indeavours by ſeveral ſorts of men, beſides theſe; ſome of them I may meet with at another turn, others a reaſonable underſtanding will anſwer; and therefore I will go no further in this.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Have you not ſome other conſideration about the Scriptures meet to be opened? you ſpake a little before of the Dignity of the ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, will you prove thoſe ſayings?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I did ſo, and before I go further, I think it meet to do that work, for now having proved the Scriptures to be of divine Authority, we may with all boldneſs apply our ſelves unto them, as a ſafe guide in Religion. And firſt for the Dignity of the ten Commandments, it is moſt evident that they are a ſuperior Law, on which all other Laws in the Scriptures depend. For this, ſee Chriſt's own Teſtimony, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.35. where giving us the ſum of that divine Law, conſiſting in Love to God and to our Neighbour, he tells us in expreſs words, that the whole
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105197:7"/>Law and the Prophets hang upon it; and that this is not my own expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Text, but the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls,</hi> ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.8, 9, 10. as alſo <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.8, 9, 10, 11. how plainly doth he there call this Law the Royal Law; and that this is the Law there intended, plainly appears, by his naming ſome of the Precepts of it expreſly.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But theſe two Texts,</hi> Romans <hi>and</hi> James, <hi>ſeem to look to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table more than the firſt; muſt we underſtand the whole ten is there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, although not expreſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The whole Law is expreſt truly in thoſe Texts, although not ſo largely handled; the Apoſtles buſineſs being to apply the ſecond Table to thoſe preſent caſes; but Love belongs to God as wel as to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; and the ſecond Table without the firſt, cannot be every tittle of the Royal Law; which yet appeareth more clearly, if you conſider that the way to prove our Love to men to be ſincere, is by our Love to God, and keeping of his Commandments, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.2, 3. And the Commands without limitation, are ſaid to be the whole duty of man, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13. And <hi>David</hi> found the keeping of them all, the only ſafe way of eſcaping ſhame, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6. And in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111. how vehemently he preſſes the keeping of thoſe Commands that are the work of God's hands, which none were but only the ten Commandments, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. theſe he wrote twice himſelf, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.15, 16. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. And how <hi>Moſes</hi> exalted them above all other Laws of God, ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But can you by ſome further opening the point, help our underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, that we may diſcern that the whole Scriptures do depend upon them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Very evident it is in Reaſon, that this Law is of a Supream Authority: for obſerve, the judicial Law clearly dependeth upon it; for it is a Law ordaining puniſhments for the tranſgreſſions of that high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Law. And as for the Ceremonial Law, it dependeth upon it plainly; for it conſiſteth of ſhadows of Chriſt, and the Grace that comes to the world by him; who came to redeem us from the curſe of that Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. And from theſe and other-like Texts, we may clearly ſee that the whole Goſpel dependeth upon that Law alſo: for it being tranſgreſſed by all mankind, and no poſſibility therefore for any man to have life by the Law, becauſe it curſed every tranſgreſſor without Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: and ſeeing all are gone out of the way, and are altogether become abominable, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. &amp; 53. and therefore no juſtification by the Law. And therefore if God would be ſo gracious as to ſave man, there lay this neceſſity upon him to give his Son to die, and through his Blood, to vouchſafe his Word, Spirit and Ordinances, and whatſoever tendeth to juſtifie or to ſanctifie man, and ſo to fit him for Eternal Life. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105197:7"/>the whole Scriptures conſiſting of threatenings for ſin, committed againſt that Law, or declarations of the judgements that have fallen upon the tranſgreſſors of that Law; or promiſes of mercy to thoſe that obey it, or repent for breaking it; or declarations of the bleſſings which they have had, or ſhall have, that love or obſerve it; or ſome or other ſuch head of Doctrine is held forth in the whole Scriptures fome way relating to that Law, that what Doctrine ſoever we hear at any time, that beareth not a good accord with that Law of the ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, we are taught by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> to believe that that Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>hath no light in him,</hi> Iſa. 8.20. So that whoſoever will but mind the Scriptures, and exerciſe his reaſon, may very well diſcern they all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon that Law.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Will you ſhew us how they be the foundation of all Religion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, That which hath been ſaid, is a full proof that they be the foundation of all Religion; for if they be the ground of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, Exhortation, Promiſes, and whatſoever elſe is contained in the Scriptures, then muſt they needs be the foundation of all Religion, if Religion be to be learned from the Scriptures, as ſure it is, and they be the Counſels and Words of God, as they have been proved to be.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But what if the Scriptures be the Words of God, may nothing be learned from the Church; is there nothing in her power to order in manner of God's Worſhip, or the time of it; is there no ceremony or cuſtome lawful but what the Scriptures warrant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No, nothing is lawful in God's Worſhip, but his own certain Appointments: He hath by an expreſs Law bound us to hearken to his Word, and neither add nor diminiſh, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2. with many other-like Texts.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But are we not as well commanded not to forſake the Law of our Mother, as to obey the Commands of our Father,</hi> Prov. 1.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.20. <hi>and is not the Church our Mother?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That Popiſh interpretation of thoſe Texts, appears to be I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous and blaſphemous: the admitting the Church to be a law-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Mother, if you compare it with the words of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.9. where the commandments of men, although they were the Church, are condemned for vain worſhip. Alſo <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, Chriſt is in all things head to the Church, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.22. and if that Apoſtle underſtood him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, there can be nothing left for the Church to order or appoint, in one kind or other, about God's Worſhip; but her work lies meerly in ſearching out what her Head by himſelf, or by his Miniſtry hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Who account you Chriſt's Miniſtry?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:105197:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All the Pen-men of the holy Scriptures, as well thoſe that wrote the Old Teſtament, as thoſe that wrote the New, as appears, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Can you make it a little more plain to our underſtandings, that the ten Commandments are the ground and foundation of all Religion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That I ſhall indeavour, and for that end conſider, there muſt be a Law binding all men to the obſervance of God's Will, before any ſin can be committed; and it muſt be a Law of ſuch a nature, as ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the whole world guilty before God, according to <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. and no ſuch Law can be found but the ten Commandments.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Is it not more likely to be that Law, written in the hearts of all men, ſpoken of,</hi> Rom. 2. <hi>that brings the whole world under guilt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> True it is; but that Law written in the heart, is the very ſame Law; as is plainly to be ſeen in that 2d to the <hi>Rom.</hi> 14, 15. and ſo to the end of the Chapter. The very ſame Law that the <hi>Jews</hi> boaſted of, and preached, and ſhall be judged by, it is that that is writ in the heart, and may be diſcerned by the Light aforded to natural men. And the Gentiles come up to a more cloſe obedience of, than the Jews, and ſo have more praiſe of God, and be in his account the better Jews: the only difference is, the one hath it written in letters eaſie to read, the other only as it is written in the heart: but the Law is the very ſame that is given both to the one and to the other.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Was there no Religion in the world, till the ten Commandments were given upon Mount Sinai?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, from the very beginning of the world, but yet not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ten Commandments were given, for there could be none with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But how doth it appear that the ten Commandments were given to Adam and all his Poſterity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Law could not ſtop every mouth, and bring the whole world under guilt, if <hi>Adam,</hi> the Father of the whole world, were not under it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Do you read of any other command to him, then to forbear the fruit of the Tree, of knowledge of Good and Evil?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea we do, or may do; if through careleſneſs and inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration we over look them not: For can it be reaſonably thought, that God ſanctified the Sabbath for no uſe; which abſurdity cannot be av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if it were not for <hi>Adam</hi> to keep: or that <hi>Cain</hi> ſinned in killing his Brother, if there had been no Law againſt Murther: or indeed that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Godlineſs or Righteouſneſs was like to flouriſh in the world, if any of the ten Commandments had been wanting. But further it is clear,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105197:8"/>that the ten Commands are called the Firſt Covepant o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Old Covenant; <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. And in the 9th chap. 15. ver. there you have the Cauſe of Chriſt's Death, rendered to be for the ſins committed againſt that firſt Covenant. So that it is evident beyond contradiction, that if <hi>Abel, Enoch,</hi> and the godly Patriarchs of the firſt Ages of the world, had the benifit of the Redeemers blood; for otherwiſe they could not be righteous by Faith, then the New Covenant muſt needs be in force in <hi>Adams</hi> dayes: And I am ſure no man in his right mind, will ſay, that the New Covenant is older than the old Covenant is.</p>
            <p>Again, can it be any other than that holy Law which is ſo well known in the Old Teſtament, that <hi>Paul</hi> doth mean, when he maketh the work of Redemption to lie in delivering us from the curſe of the Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. &amp; 4.4.5. Therefore they do not want ignorance, that have ſo confidently affirmed, that the Sabbath, which is one of the ten Words, was never given to the Gentiles, neither by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor by the Law of Nature, nor yet by the Law of Chriſt. Seeing it is ſo evident in reaſon to believe, that what was given to the firſt Fathers of the world, was given to the World. And the curſe of that Law that did neceſſitate the Death of Chriſt for the World, muſt needs be the Worlds duty, otherwiſe it could not curſe them; but they ſhew themſelves what skilful builders they be.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Seeing you charge theſe men ſo home, ſpeak one word more for the further clearing of this point?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, Then it is evident to all men, that as many as were bound to be circumciſed, were bound to keep the whole Law. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is full in <hi>Pauls</hi> words, beyond any reaſonable mans doubt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.3. for if he was bound to keep the whole Law, who was circumciſed; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, there might be ſome circumciſed, who at that day, when <hi>Paul</hi> wrote this, it was not their duty, but their ignorance ſo to be; How much more muſt they needs be bound to keep the Law, who were bound to be circumciſed, whether they were circumciſed or no? except the neglect of one duty diſcharged a man of all other due from him to his God, which I preſume no man will ſay. So that here remains nothing to do but only this, namely, to prove, That all men before the coming of Chriſt in the fleſh, were bound to be circumciſed: and if it had not been the Worlds duty as well as Iſraels, wherefore ſhould be Lord threaten to puniſh them for the neglect of it, as he doth? <hi>Jerem.</hi> 9.25, 26. Sure God will not puniſh them for that which is no ſin: and it can be no ſin to neglect that which is no duty. Again, <hi>Paul</hi> in drawing up his Charge againſt the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> eſtate, 2.13. before their converſion, chargeth them with the uncircumciſion of their fleſh, which ſure he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105197:9"/>would not have done, if he had not known their neglect of it before Chriſt was made known to them, had been their ſin. Again, no man can be ignorant of this, that ſtrangers that were not of Iſrael, might partake with them in all the Priviledges of Religion acceptably, that ever read <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48, 49. with other-like places: and can any man be ſo brutiſh, as to think it was not all the Gentiles duty as well as ſome of them; or to think that any of them could have been accepted, if it had been voluntary religion, or will-worſhip, ſo plainly condemneds, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.18, 23. Beſides it is manifeſt, that the very Congregation to whom God proclaimed this Law in <hi>Sinai,</hi> conſiſted of a mixed multitude of other People, as well as of <hi>Jews, Exod.</hi> 12.38. <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.4. Now that theſe ten Commandments are the foundation of all Religion, is no way hard to conceive; for becauſe this Law was tranſgreſſed, and therefore could not ſave man, therefore there was a neceſſity of our Lords Death to redeem man, as may by comparing theſe with other-like Texts toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be ſeen, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3, 4. &amp; 10.5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10, 12, 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.7, 8, 9. and 9.15. And becauſe Chriſt hath redeemed us, therefore the Goſpel is neceſſary to open to the Sons of men, the benefits of his Death: For the raiſing of Faith in the ſoul, and the working of us to repentance, and for the carrying on of the work of Sanctification, the Ordinances of the Lord's Supper, Baptiſm, and the reſt of his Appointments, are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, as Preaching, Praying, and all other duties of Plety and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs: the whole body of Religion hath ſo natural a dependance, one part of Truth upon another, and the whole of it upon that Law, as is clear and eaſie to every conſidering man to underſtand.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But is not this Doctrine legal, and an exalting the Law above the Gospel, in ſaying it is the foundation of Religion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No by no means, no ſuch thing will follow, no more than it will follow that the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> is greater than the ſecond <hi>Adam;</hi> or the darkneſs more excellent than the light, although that was firſt created.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Explain this point as brief as you can.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Underſtand it thus, I call this Law the Foundation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, becauſe if it be made void, all Religion of neceſſity muſt be made void with it. As for Example, if it continue not to be a rule of holy and juſt living, then he that neglecteth to obſerve it, ſinneth not; and he that offendeth not this Law, cannot be cuiſed by it; and he that is not curſed by it, cannot ſtand in need of redemption by our Lord Jeſus to redeem him from the curſe thereof; and he that needs no Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, needs no Redeemer; and he that needs not a Redeemer, needs not the bleſſings that come by him, nor yet a Goſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nor Ordinances to convey them to him: So that if you mind it well, you will ſee that all
<pb facs="tcp:105197:9"/>the parts and prancies of Religion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Law; therefore as we love Religion, and would ſee it proſper, let u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be tender of the root. Our Saviour tells us, not one jor or tittle ſhall paſs from this Law; and that he that breaketh one of the leaſt of them, <hi>ſhall be called the leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Mat. 5.18, 19. And <hi>James</hi> will not allow the breach of it in one point, but requires the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of it, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Doth the Law ſtand in the ſame force and power now, as when it was at firſt given, becauſe the Scriptures ſpeak of it, as old and done away, dead to us, and we to it, with ſuch-like expreſſions which make ſome think, it doth not continue to be a Rule of life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, The Law continues the ſame in it ſelf for ever, and is an everlaſting Rule of Godlineſs and Righteouſneſs to all Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as hath been proved: nevertheleſs, the Law hath no power to help our diſtreſſes, which we lie in now ſince the Fall, but our help com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by our Lord Jeſus alone. As for example, It cannot juſtifie us, not ſanctifie us; look <hi>Rom.</hi> 3d, 4th &amp; 7th chapters, with many more Texts like them: It cannot now give us life, although once it was ordained for that purpoſe, but it is now become the Miniſtration of Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a killing letter, out of whoſe power there were no eſcaping, were not its curſing Office taken out of its hands by Jeſus Chriſt; look <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. with other-like places: but I cannot now ſtand to diſcourſe this at large, it would require a Book of it ſelf; nevertheleſs, I was willing to give thee a little hint or notice of theſe things, to preſerve thee from ſtumbling at this holy Law, as many blind and ignorant ſouls do, who will not have it at all; that becauſe it will not ſerve them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will not have it cendemn them, nor ſhew them their ſin; but this Office it will have in the world to the end of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>If the whole and every tittle of the Law be for ever binding, then the fourth Command muſt be binding alſo; and that almoſt all men are againſt; ſome think it aboliſhed, and that we are bound to keep no Sabhath at all; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers think it partly moral, and partly ceremonial; others think the Church had power to change it; others think the Apoſtles and Church in their dayes changed it; others think that a ſeventh part of time at the will and pleaſure of man, is ſufficient inſtead of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer in the words of the Prophet, <hi>The Lord knoweth the thoughts of men that they are vanity,</hi> Pſal. 94.11. for there is no ground for any of theſe thoughts, but the fourth Command is like its fellows, given at the beginning of the world, and endures as long as the world endures.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Will you ſpeak a few words to prove its Perpetuity in particular?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105197:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That I ſhall; but ſeeing there are ſo many Treatiſes extant, of ſo many Authors, ſome dead, and ſome living, that have ſo fully proved it, and anſwered all objections, I ſhall ſay the leſs, <hi>Brayborn, Ocford, Spitlehouſe, Stenit,</hi> with many others I omit to name now; yet notwithſtanding I ſhall ſay ſomething heat; <hi>Firſt,</hi> It was given in a day of Innocency, even the very firſt whole day of <hi>Adams</hi> being in the world, which is enough to deliver it from all ſuſpition of being ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial or changeable, but a ſanctified ſeaſon to worſhip God in, and to commemorate the Work of Creation for ever.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>The ſecond of</hi> Geneſis <hi>ſpeaks of God's reſting upon it, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying it; but is it plain that he gave it to</hi> Adam, <hi>and ſo to the world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For anſwer to this, when God ſanctified the Sabbath, it muſt be for <hi>Adam,</hi> or for himſelf: now it is ſo ſorded to ſay, or to think, that he ſanctified a Reſt for himſelf, that one would think that no man that is in his right mind, would once imagine it. As for outward Reſt, he cannot want, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.28. and for inward Sanctification, he can have as little want of that; for who that owneth a God, will not confeſs him to be perfect, now if he had no need to ſanctifie it for himſelf, he did it for <hi>Adam,</hi> or for no uſe at all; but to judge him ſo vain in his actions, is too great blaſphemy for any to affirm that hath his reaſon, and doth but uſe it.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Have you any thing more to ſtrengthen this proof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, when the Lord gave it with the other nine, in the 20. of <hi>Exodus,</hi> he placed it in the midſt of his Law, and wrote it with his own hand, and put it into the Ark with its fellows, and fenced it about with more Reaſons to preſerve it from violation, than he did all the other ſix Commands following it; and all thoſe Reaſons are of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral nature, not one of them otherwiſe; ſo that here is no occaſion given of mens ſo ſtumbling at it, as they do; but that the Duty is <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> and mens hearts <hi>carnal,</hi> and they love to be ruled by the fleſh.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But is there not ground to judge the Sabbath ceremonial from that</hi> 2d <hi>of the</hi> Coloſſians?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not at all, if men did with care read and conſider the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; for evident it is, that beſides the New Moons, and holy Dayes, of which there were many, there were four ceremonial Sabbaths in the ſeventh Month, as appears, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.24, 32, 39. which if conſidered, men would be wiſer than to imploy that Text in that unworthy Service, to take away the Seventh-Day-Sabbath, eſpecially ſeeing the Sabbaths there mentioned, are of the nature of the New Moons &amp; holy Days, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of things to come; but the Seventh-Day-Sabbath, appointed to commemorate the great Work paſt. But further, when God decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:105197:10"/>his ten Commandments in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, but the Seventh-Day, burgiveth his People in this Command, as free leave to work the ſix dayes, as if he never intended any other Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath ſhould be kept at all, and yet by <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſhortly after giveth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for them alſo. All which ſheweth plainly the difference between theſe two ſorts of Sabbaths, the one to contitute a Law for ever, the other a ſhadow till the time of Reformation only.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Seeing it is ſo oppoſed in the world, ſpeak one word or two more for its confirmation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Our Lord Jeſus hath in the Now Teſtament, ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed it; Firſt in general, By telling that the Law, in which the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath is included, ſhall remain in every jot and tittle of it, till Heaven and Earth paſs away, and till all things be fulfilled: now we know ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great things, ſpoken of in the Law and Prophets, are not yet fulfilled; neither is Heaven and Earth in any ſence paſſed away, and therefore the Sabbath muſt remain by that Rule, without the diminiſhing of one tittle of it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17, 18, 19, 20. theſe Texts are of a like import with that already named, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.17, 18. <hi>Jawes.</hi> 2.8, 10, 11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. and 12.17. &amp; 14.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.1, 2, 3. with many other.</p>
            <p>Again, in particular to the Sabbath it ſelf; If our Lord did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it ſhould continue after his Death, but he nailed to the Croſs with the other Ceremonies, what reaſon could there be for him to adviſe his Diſciples to pray that their flight might not fall out on the Sabbath, or at the fall of <hi>Jeruſalens,</hi> ſeeing it fell out ſorty years after his Death? and wherefore ſhould be tell us it was made for man, and that He is the Lord of it, if it have no being in his Dominions amongſt the Children of men? <hi>Mark</hi> 2.27, 28. And beſides all this, doth not the holy Spirit call it Sabbath; and how dare mortal worms call it working day? For which way can it deſerve the name of a Sabbath, if it retain not the nature of a Sabbath? But this is an Age in which men are bent to walk in their own wayes, and neither believe nor do any thing that croſſeth the fleſh; otherwiſe how were it poſſible for men to find ſo many eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to keep off from ſo plain a Duty? which was the conſtant practice of the Saints in the Primitive time, as may be ſeen, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.14, 42, 44. and 16.13. &amp; 17.2. &amp; 18.4. And it is obſervable, that in the former of theſe Texts, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. <hi>Paul</hi> keeps Sabbath with Gentiles, and ſpeaks not the leaſt word againſt their Practice, nor intimates nothing of a meeting any other day, an evil that <hi>Paul</hi> would never have been guilty of, had he known any thing of the aboliſhing or changing of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-day; for how earneſtly <hi>Paul</hi> contended againſt the Gentiles obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Ceremonies, cannot be unknown.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105197:11"/>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But is it not poſſible for the whole ten Commands to be obſerved, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Sabbath be tranſmitted from the ſeventh to the firſt day of the week?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the Lord, or any other by his Authority, had ſo done, I would not have queſtioned his power or wiſdom herein; but ſeeing he did it not, but it is meerly an invention of man, I muſt condemn it for a wicked and ungodly Practice, of which the old Serpent was the principal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, to cauſe the poor Jews to ſtumble at the Redeemer of the World to this day.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Since Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and Primitive Saints obſerved it, what is the reaſon that the Jews do not believe in Jeſus Chriſt, ſeeing Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-Prophanation is one of their greateſt Arguments they commonly urge againſt Chriſt, and the Chriſtian Religion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is no cauſe to wonder at their unbelief, nor at the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it; for how can we expect they ſhould ſearch the New Teſtament diligently, to inform themſelves what the mind and practice of Chriſt and his Primitive Saints was, when they who profeſs it to be their Rule, are ſo extream careleſs in this matter, that they ſuffer themſelves to be couzened, ſome with another day, and ſome with no day, inſtead of the Sabbath: now the poor Jews judging of the Religion of Chriſt, by the lives of the generality of thoſe that profeſs his Name, cannot but ſtumble at him, and abominate that Religion that alloweth ſuch plain and noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Wickedneſs, committed againſt the expreſs letter of God's moſt holy Law; and it cannot be expected in reaſon that they ſhould repent and believe, till a more general Reformation be found in the lives of the Gentiles, that profeſs to believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Well if ſuch prejudices as they take at the Lord Jeſus, ſhould be removed, how can it be clearly proved that Chriſt Jeſus, the Son of Mary, who was crucified by</hi> Pilate, <hi>is the true Meſſiah?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There are many infallible proofs of it; As firſt, The certain Time of his coming, being ſo fairly pointed at by the Scriptuies; if Jeſus be not he, this will follow, not only that we muſt with the Jews look for another, but be conſtrained alſo to caſt off the holy Scriptures, received both by them and us, and ſo ſhall be wholly at a loſs to know what to believe or receive for truth, in order to our eternal peace.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Name ſome of thoſe Texts, and a little open them, for the ſakes of the poor Jews, and the blind World; who, it is to be feared, neither know Him, nor in truth believe in Him, but ignorantly confeſs him, becauſe it is the Religion of the Times, and tradition and cuſtom hath taught them ſo to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The firſt Text is <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. <hi>The Scepter ſhall not depart from Judah, and the Law-giver from between his feet, until Shiloh come, and unto
<pb facs="tcp:105197:11"/>him ſhal the obedience of the Peoples <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hiloh</hi> here is Chriſt, or the Meſſiah, and ſo underſtood by the Hebrew Doctors, as well as by Chriſtians. See learned <hi>Ainſworth</hi> upon the place: And that he was to come according to <hi>Jacobs</hi> Propheſie, at or near the time that the Kings and Governours of <hi>Judah</hi> ceaſed to rule, is the manifeſt ſcope and intent of the Text: And although <hi>Judah</hi> had no King after the Captivity, yet her Princes were ſtill known, and by Permiſſion ſome of them bore Rule, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, <hi>Ezra</hi> 3.8, 9. <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.12. And evident it is, the Heirs of the Crown of <hi>Judah,</hi> were well known to the coming of Chriſt, and Chriſt known to be Heir apparent to the Crown of <hi>Judah</hi> ſo well, that when he wrought that Miracle of feeding five thouſand with five loaves, and two fiſhes, <hi>John</hi> 6.14, 15. the people would by force have made him King, if he had not by hiding himſelf avoided it; and that was a charge againſt him at his death, that he was King of the Jews; but neither <hi>Pilate</hi> nor the Jews could deny but that ſo He was; his right to the Crown may well be perceived, by what his enemies on both parts ſay, in that 18, &amp; 19, chapters of <hi>John.</hi> but ſince Chriſt, the World, nor the Jews themſelves, cannot find any Law-giver or Prince that ſo much as pretended a right to the Kingdom, but are ſo diſperſed and broken, that they are like to find none, till that Prophecy be fulfilled, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. that they look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him whom they pierced, to whom the Peoples, that is, the Gentiles, do gather, acknowledge or obey, according to this Text; and impoſſible it is, that this Text can be fulfilled in any that is yet to come; for the Houſe of <hi>Judah</hi> hath been without a Governour or Law-giver this 1600 years at leaſt, and ſo long ago, or longer, the Meſſiah muſt be come, or elſe this Text muſt be blotted out of the Book of God: and if once <hi>Moſes</hi>'s writings come into queſtion, then farewel all Religion both among Jews and Gentiles. Now as for our Lord Jeſus, we know that all Prophecies of the Old Teſtament are fulfilled in him; He is a Prophet like to <hi>Moſes,</hi> moſt graciouſly opening and confirming all the moral Laws; and in his own obedience unto the Death, fulfilled all the ceremonial Laws; and the Laws he hath added in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are ſo fully confirmed by many glorious Miracles, and are ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, juſt, and good, the end of them all tending to advance Love with Holineſs: Witneſs Baptiſm, the Lord's Supper, and the reſt of his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments; ſo that to his time, and in him, this Prophecy of good old Father <hi>Jacob</hi> is fulfilled; but ſince him there hath been no Law-giver to the Houſe of <hi>Judah,</hi> and therefore the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> cannot be to come, unleſs we ſhould reject <hi>Moſes</hi>'s writings, and account them fables, which God forbid. The other two Texts are <hi>Haggai,</hi> the 2.7, 9. and <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.1. In the former of theſe Texts, you have a Promiſe made to
<pb facs="tcp:105197:12"/>
               <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> that the deſire of all Nations ſhould come, and that the Temple he built, ſhould be filled with Glory; yea, have greater Glory than the former built by <hi>Solomon,</hi> although it were in compariſon of it as nothing; yea, ſo great a difference was there between them, for all outward glory, that the old men that had ſeen the firſt Houſe, lamented the meanneſs of this latter Houſe, as much as the young men rejoyced at its Glory, <hi>Ezra</hi> 3.12, 13. So that it is evident to every indifferent and impartial man, that the coming of Chriſt to that Houſe while it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained, ſhould be the great Glory promiſed to it. Likewiſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in <hi>Malachi</hi> cuts off all cavels about the matter, for there the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe runs clear, <hi>The Lord whom ye ſeek ſhall ſuddenly come to his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Meſſenger of the Covenant, whom ye delight in.</hi> And if it be conſidered, no man can doubt but that our Lord Jeſus is the Chriſt, who did come to that Temple, and by his Preſence, and bleſſed Doctrine, made it glorious, even while it was yet ſtanding: for if theſe Texts be not fulfilled in Chriſt our Lord, they never can be fulfilled at all; for the Promiſes were made of his coming, to that Temple which <hi>Zerubba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> built, and cannot be underſtood of one that is yet to be built, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it ſhould be built the next month; for that can never be ſaid to be done ſuddenly, that remains ſo many hundred years undone, as it is ſince <hi>Malachi</hi> wrote; neither if the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſhould come to another Temple not yet in being, would it ſignifie any thing as to the fulfilling of any Promiſe made concerning that Temple, then which <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> built; but the Promiſes were made to that Temple then known and in being, if ever thoſe Prophets intended their meaning ſhould be known by their words; and therefore we muſt own our Lord Jeſus for the true Meſſiah and Saviour of mankind, or elſe reject <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, or put out the eye of our underſtanding and reaſon.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Have you ſome further proof of this great Truth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The glorious Miracles which he did in the dayes of his fleſh, and his Miniſters after him, ſo plentifully recorded in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be an evident witneſs of the truth of his being ſent of God; Who, that is not aſſiſted with omnipotency, can give eyes to the blind, yea, to thoſe born blind; and cure ſuch as are lame from the womb; caſt out Devils by a word of command; raiſe the dead four dayes dead, with cures of all kinds?</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But may not an unbelieving perſon ſay, how ſhall the truth of all this be known?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I ſay, where is the Book, the Author, or Record, that could ever be produced, that hath ſubſtantially diſcovered the falfity of the Records of the New Teſtament? if not, we may be ſure it is moſt
<pb facs="tcp:105197:12"/>true; for there never wanted either malice or skill to have done it, if it could poſſibly have been done.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Is there any further proof of this, becauſe it is a point of great importance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Prophecies that went before of him where he ſhould be born, and of whom, a Virgin of the Houſe of <hi>David;</hi> what he ſhould ſuffer, and by what hands; how he ſhould be numbred with tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, be pierced, his garments parted, lots caſt upon his veſture, and He ſold for 30 pieces of Silver, which ſhould come into the Potters hands; with whatſoever was written in the Old Teſtament of the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah, it was to a tittle fulfilled in our Lord Jeſus, and that in the very let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it; ſo that here is no place left for our doubting, if malice blind not our underſtandings.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Is there any thing more to be ſaid to this point?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, this may be further added as a proof in the caſe, The holineſs &amp; unſpottedneſs of his Life and Doctrine. As for his Doctrine it ſpeaks for its ſelf, and lies fair to be ſeen in the New Teſtament; and as for his Life, although many ſcandals were raiſed upon him, as if he were a friend of publicans and ſinners, a Devil, a Sabbath-breaker, yet no jot of this dirt can ſtick to this ſpotleſs Lamb; for whoſoever ſhall make the cloſeſt ſearch and ſcruteny into his actions, ſhall ſee that, that which ſeems moſt probable to be true, is moſt falſe; how far are his cures on the Sabbath from breaking the Sabbath? the man that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to carry his bed, who had been 38 years ſick, was an action ſo far from breaking the Sabbath, that there was nothing like that could have been done or ſaid, that could have preached Chriſt ſo convincing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Conſciences of men, to be the Anointed of God, that they might believe and be ſaved; ſo neither this nor any thing elſe can manifeſt the leaſt evil in him; but contrarily, his Life is ſo innocent, that in the face of his greateſt oppoſers, he could ſay, <hi>Which of you convinceth me of ſin?</hi> John 8.46.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Indeed Holineſs is a glorious Argument, and much tends to ſtop an enemies mouth; but if you have another, let us hear it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I have two more, and the firſt of them is, The conſtant Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of all true Believers in all Ages; never did any perſon go to the Father by prayer and ſupplication in his neceſſity, asking in Chriſt's Name, and according to his Commandment believing in Him, that ever was diſappointed of his hope. This not only I have many hundred ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences of, but it is a general caſe; all the truly Faithful ſince Chriſt to this day, can ſet their ſeal to this Truth.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Experience is a ſtrong Argument, but let us hear your ſixth and laſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:105197:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> My laſt is not my leaſt, it is taken from that glorious Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony that God gave of him in his Death and Reſurrection. Firſt at his Death, The Darkneſs that was from the ſixth hour to the ninth; that is, from that you call 12 a Clok, to that you call 3 a Clok in the afternoon, is a clear manifeſtation, that God accounted his enemies cruelty againſt him, a blak action; for this darkneſs could come from no natural cauſe, the Paſsover being alwayes at a Full Moon, and therefore in the North and North-Eaſt at that time of the day, far enough from cauſing any Eclipſe, and he died at the time of the Paſsover, all this is beyond diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Vaile of the Temple rent in twain, from the top to the bottome, this being a hanging of Twenty Cubites long, where it was by the Miniſters of the Temple, Chriſt's deadly enemies, kept ſafe enough from any hand of earthly man, none but a Meſſenger from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven could rent it; again, the Earth did quake, and the Rocks rent, which could not be, but by an omnipotent Power; all which made the Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion and his Company, though in all probability they were Heathens, being Souldiers in Caeſars Army, cry out, and ſay, <hi>Truly this was the Son of God;</hi> and if Souldiers, who are commonly rude perſons, eſpecially when they have ſuch Maſters as they had, if they could not chuſe but ſee this, how much more ſhould all men conſider and take notice of God's Teſtimony ſo gloriouſly born on his behalf. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt proves it beyond exception.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Yea, but how ſhall that be proved clearly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There be three evident proofs of it; 1. The witneſſes of it are a conſiderable number, not leſs than Five hundred at once, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.6, 7, 8. and ſome of theſe died for this Teſtimony; and what their holy Doctrine and Life was, is to be ſeen in the New Teſtament, and neither credit nor profit was to be gained by this Teſtimony; beſides two of theſe witneſſes were ſuch, as had they not been extraordinarily convinced of the truth of it, would not have believed it themſelves: <hi>Thomas</hi> proclaiming his unbelief, till he felt and ſaw the print of the nailes, and thruſt his hand into his ſide, which the Spear had made, <hi>John</hi> 20.24, 25. And as for <hi>Paul,</hi> he perſecuted this Teſtimony unto the death, and had his hand in the blood of <hi>Stephen</hi> for it, not altering his bloody purpoſe, till by a Voice and a Light from Heaven, he was ſmitten blind, and unto the earth, and he made to know, that that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus whom he perſecuted in his People, was riſien and aſcended. 2. The miſerable excuſe that was made to blind the Peoples underſtandings, that they might not believe he was riſen, proves it evidently; for he was laid in a Tomb which had a ſtone ſo great on the top of it, that the good women were in care to get it removed, when they came to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105197:13"/>him. Alſo there was a ſtrong guard of Souldiers ſet to watch, leſt his Diſciples ſhould ſteal him, who were ſo afraid of their own lives, that they durſt not meet but in the night, an unlikely company to ſteal their Maſters dead body from a band of Souldiers. But now to make the world believe that theſe poor frighted men ſtole him away while they ſlept, is moſt impoſſible; for who can believe that the whole Guard ſhould be aſleep all at once? or who can believe his Diſciples durſt venture to roul off that Stone in the midſt of thoſe Armed men, to ſteal his Corps from them, they being ſet there on purpoſe to prevent them from this act? muchleſs was it poſſible for them to be able to give a juſt account whether he were ſtollen away, or riſen again, if they had been all aſleep indeed; and it is not at all likely, that thoſe armed Souldiers ran from the Sepulchre to the High Prieſt in ſuch a fear, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Diſciples had ſtole him; but indeed becauſe the Angel of the Lord terrified them away from that fruitleſs work: Neither yet can it enter into any mans heart to believe, that ever the Prieſts and Elders of the <hi>Jews,</hi> would ever go about to perſwade the Governour to peace and reconciliation with thoſe Souldiers, that had ſo much neglected their duty, to ſuffer him to be ſtole, if indeed he had been ſtole, but they would much rather have perſwaded him to take them, and hang them up eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man of them, for their negligence, if it had not manifeſtly appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that Jeſus, whom they cauſed to be crucified, was indeed riſen again from the dead. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> and laſtly, Beſides the wonderful Miracles his Apoſtles did work in his Name; the Gifts beſtowed upon them ſo ſuddenly after his Aſcention, according to the Promiſe made to them, the which we read of, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1, to the 11. proves it clearly: for from whence could poor Fiſher-men, ignorant and unlearned, at an inſtance attain ſuch Gifts of Knowledge, Courage, Utterance, as is there ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, but that it muſt needs be by the Power of the holy Spirit? To all which I only ask this queſtion, I deſire that the moſt unbelieving Jews, will tell me what they expect from the Meſſiah they look for, or what they can think he ſhould be, that Jeſus Chriſt is not? When this is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly anſwered, I will ſet Pen to Paper again, if the Lord pleaſe that I live to ſee it; in the mean time, as one deſiring the Salvation both of Jews and Gentiles, I intreat all men to conſider the main grounds of Religion, and to get ſuch ſound Principles for the Foundation thereof, as will ſubſtantially bear up the whole body of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:105197:14"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A brief Anſwer to</hi> William Ruſſel, <hi>in a Book of his, entituled,</hi> No Seventh-Day-Sabbath in Chriſt's New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
            <p>ALthough that which I have written already, is enough to ſtop the mouths of all Oppoſers of God's moſt holy Law, yet becauſe the ignorance and folly of men is ſo great in this day, I ſhall add a few words to what I have written already, upon the occaſion of a late Book I have ſeen, intituled, <hi>The Seventh-Day-Sabbath not Commanded by Jeſus Chriſt in the New Teſtament;</hi> but I deſire thee, good Reader, not to expect that I ſhould waſte my time, or be at the coſt, to follow <hi>William Ruſſel</hi> with a Reply to that green-headed Piece of his, that conſiſteth for the moſt part of it, of Debates and Reaſonings of other men; but I ſhall apply my ſelf to touch briefly ſome few paſſages aſſerted by <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>And firſt, to that learned Aſſertion in the 12th page of his Book, where he concludeth, ſince his eyes were opened, that the <hi>Ten Words being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed, as the firſt Covenant, to do for Life, they cannot continue as a Rule of Life; the diſtinction is ſo nice, that it is groundleſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, It is well you confeſs them to be the firſt Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and once given for Life; the good Lord give thee and others Wiſdom to take notice of the time when it was ſo given, for it could never give Life; therefore it muſt be in that day when it would have continued Life to eternity, if it had been kept; and therefore be not ſo witleſs as to think, that when God gave his Law at <hi>Sinai,</hi> as a Rule of Life, (for thy ſelf confeſſeſt that ſo he did to Jews and Proſelytes) that then he intended it as a Covenant to do for Life; for if he did, he muſt intend to condemn them all: for nothing is more evident, than that they were all ſinners; and impoſſible it is, that thou canſt deny it to be againſt this Law they ſinned: For thou affirmeſt in the 37 page of thy Book, <hi>That the New Covenant was not in force till after the Death of Chriſt;</hi> therefore they could not, according to thy judgement, ſin againſt that Covenant: and thy ſelf confeſſeſt in the 23 page, <hi>That there is but two, a firſt and a ſecond;</hi> and that is the only Truth, almoſt, aſſerted by thee; for ſuch a piece of ignorance and folly, I think never ſaw the light.
<pb facs="tcp:105197:14"/>ever under the curſe of it, it is a poor priviledge the Jew had above the Gentile; <hi>Mr. Jves</hi> will not conſent to this, I believe, for it takes away the main Piller of all his building: but your skill in the ſtudy of Divinity is well ſeen, when this diſtinction is too nice for you: You are like to make good ſence of the Epiſtles to the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Galatians,</hi> and the Scriptures in general; therefore for ſhame retract thy work, and buy a Catechiſm, and place thy ſelf under the Miniſtry of ſome guide, that is able to inſtruſt thee in the main Points of Religion at leaſt, that thou be not a ſhame to thy ſelf, and to all that are in communion with thee. Compare theſe words with what is expreſt in the 20 page, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>That under this Law, no believing Gentile can be, becauſe it was given to none but Jews and Proſelyted Gentiles.</hi> Well, if this be all true, then the reſt of the world were under no Covenant at all. Oh rare Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty! But ſecondly, Take notice of your skill in diſtinguiſhing between Proſelyted Gentiles, and believing Gentiles, as if the Proſelytes muſt needs be unbelievers; if they believed not, what made them joyn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Lord and his People? You Sabbath-Breakers are excellent <hi>Logicians;</hi> but very ſilly in the uſe of Reaſon. Oh lay by that vain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, that makes you ſwell with folly and pride, and in humility ſearch the holy Scriptures, and be not ſo abſurd as to believe, that nothing is New Covenant, but what is writ ſince the Death of Chriſt, and given to the Gentiles, and that all given forth before, and that hath been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Jews, muſt needs be Old Covenant; theſe and ſuch-like Doctrines you would perſwade us againſt the Sabbath withal: the Lord ſend you all more wit. I have ſtriven by writing and reaſoning, all I could, to put a ſtop to thoſe ſwarms of Errors you have run into, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void Sabbath-keeping; and I intended my Book, to ſee if you would conſider it, and intended to exerciſe Patience with you yet, being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly unwilling the world ſhould know your folly: but your ſelves proclaim your own ſhame; and if I ſhould ſtill be ſilent, the world would think that we were all alike; therefore I can do no leſs than bear a Teſtimony againſt your folly, although I have ſomething elſe to do, than to follow you in your Wild-gooſe chaſe. Obſerve one note more out of the 24 page, where he confeſſeth, <hi>That all Adams unbelieving Children are bound to obſerve the firſt Covenant, and ſhall be charged if they break it.</hi> And here you may note by the way, how directly contrary he is to himſelf, in the 12 page, and 20 page. But ſecondly, he ſaith, That <hi>now ſince he believed, he is none of Adams ſtock.</hi> To this I anſwer, That if he had good ſtore of Land, ſome body would ſoon be with the King to beg him. But ſecondly, I ſay, <hi>Abel</hi> was a true believer, yet if he
<pb facs="tcp:105197:15"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> honeſt man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and yet I believe <hi>William Ruſſel</hi> is as truly deſcended from <hi>Adam</hi> as he was. And in the 20 page he denieth, that the ſecond Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Law was written in the heart of <hi>Adam,</hi> for this reaſon; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had no Neighbour. Now I ſay, no man need to wonder that the Sabbath is denied to be naturally moral, if not any of the ſix laſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands be; and ſure I believe they were never written fairer in any mans heart, than in <hi>Adams</hi> in innocency, Chriſt alone excepted: but it ſeems he doth not think the Lord wiſe enough to make a Law at once for ever, to bind all Ages and Conditions of men, but that upon every change of condition he muſt give him a new Law, or the old in a new form at leaſt.</p>
            <p>And in the 37 page, He denieth Chriſt's Mediatorſhip to be of force till ſince his Death. And in the 35 and 36 pages, he affirmeth, that, <hi>When the ten Words were given at Sinai as a Rule of Life, they were alſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to do for Life, and the breakers curſed without Mercy.</hi> The very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of theſe things, is enough to reprove the folly of them. Sure the Judgement of God is upon this mans right eye. What is become of <hi>Abraham, Moſes,</hi> and all the Patriachs and Prophets, doth he think? Or, is there any other way to Salvation, than through New-Covenant-Mercy. But now you ſee the mans heart, ſo willing he is to be rid of the Sabbath, that rather than he will keep that, he will pack the Goſpel and it out of doors together; yea, his own received Principle, the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all mankind by Jeſus Chriſt. And this is his reaſon in the 38 page, wherefore he doth not keep Sabbath; namely, <hi>Becauſe Chriſt, as Mediator of the New Teſtament, hath not commanded it; and he ſaith, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what he hath ſo commanded is his duty.</hi> Now obſerve the true conſequence of theſe opinions; if nothing be <hi>(W. R.)</hi> his duty, but what Chriſt, as Mediator, hath commanded: What neceſſity could <hi>W.</hi> ſtand in of his Death at all? for if Chriſt had not come to bring him a Law to ſin againſt, he had none it ſeems to ſin againſt before, and ſo could ſtand in no need of blood to cleanſe him?</p>
            <p>Again, if nothing be his duty, but what Chriſt hath ſo comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, then you muſt know, that no part of the Old Teſtament, nor much of the New, is any part of <hi>Williams</hi> Bible; and what need he have put himſelf to ſo much trouble, to frame ſo many quibling arguments to help himſelf againſt <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. he might have only ſaid it was given forth before the Death of Chriſt, and it had been as good as all thoſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and a thouſand more, but <hi>W.</hi> had forgot that anſwer, or elſe he truſted more to his Logick, than to that anſwer: for thoſe that have good skill in that art, can prove that a Fox hath eight legs, to him that
<pb facs="tcp:105197:15"/>never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> he may not know which is beſt to deny, the <hi>major</hi> or the <hi>minor,</hi> yet can you never perſwade him, that a Fox hath more than four legs. And for that Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. and <hi>James</hi> 2, hath more ſtrength to prove the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity of the Sabbath, than all the <hi>Logicians</hi> in <hi>Bucks</hi> can take off: and that Mr. <hi>Ives</hi> well knew, when, to rid himſelf of thoſe Texts, he told his Antagoniſts, <hi>Thoſe Books did not belong to us Gentiles, but were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Jews, and belonged only to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I cannot but obſerve one paſſage more in the 54 page of his Book, where he affirmeth, that, <hi>Our Saviours Doctrine and Practice, taught to do ſervile work on the Sabbath, repugnant to the Letter of the Law of God.</hi> This paſſage would make one think, that the man either knows not, or cares not what he ſaith; for if this were indeed true, we might well give over writing Books about Religion; for there could be no poſſibility of Salvation neither for Jew nor Gentile. For if Chriſt were a ſinner, his blood could take away no ſin; and a ſinner he muſt needs be, if he broke Sabbath, and taught others ſo to do, in a very high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, although the Sabbath had been but ceremonial; for there was no ſhadow of the Law could be neglected; the ſmalleſt of all the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, without ſin, till by Chriſts Death they were aboliſhed. But if <hi>William,</hi> had had ſo much charity for his Saviour, as to have judged him a better expounder of the Law than the Phariſees, he had not fallen into this blaſphemy: Is it not enough for the Phariſees to lay that ſin to his charge, but you muſt ſecond it, to the hardening of the poor Jews, and the deſtroying of the Faith of the Gentiles, as much as in you li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: Therefore if the Sabbath-keepers be ignorant of Chriſt's Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, as you tell your Reader they be, if they come to you for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, they are like to be well helpt up.</p>
            <p>As for your diſcourſe about what is naturally moral, and poſitively moral, it is not worth a diſpute, there is ſo little between them; the one as truly binding the Conſcience as the other: but for the Sabbath, I have ſome reaſon to believe that it is naturally moral. Firſt, There was never any people profeſſing a God, but kept one day in ſeven for his Worſhip. And there is no Precept of the firſt Table that men do come nearer to, ordinarily, that have not the expreſs Letter of the Law for their Rule. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The time is yet to come, that ever I heard or ſaw any man diſpute, or write, or preach, againſt the Sabbath; but he at that very time, and in that very work, aſſerted ſome thing that did plainly manifeſt that it was fairely written in his heart, or elſe run himſelf upon this Rock, that he ſhamefully broke the fifth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to diſpute down the fourth, as I could give inſtance if need were.
<pb facs="tcp:105197:16"/>But anſwer.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, <hi>Wherefore I am ſo ſharp in my Anſwer to</hi> W. Ruſſel?</p>
            <p>To this I ſay, I am taught of <hi>Solomon</hi> ſo to do in ſuch a caſe, as this, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.3, 4.5. 2. I was in fear he would greatly diſhonour the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel when he was going to print, and deſired to ſee his Copy, and to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with him firſt, but he would not, and 'tis juſt to laſh him that is paſt Counſel.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Queſtion I expect, is, <hi>Wherefore I do not as well anſwer</hi> Mr. <hi>Ives, as he?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſay, For his Book, Mr. <hi>Braborn</hi> hath anſwered it; but for his diſpute, I have in part, and ſhall in a few words more, give ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle account of it, the naming whereof is anſwer enough. When he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, he denied the Seventh-day-Sabbath upon this account, <hi>That it was never given to the Gentiles; neither by the Law of Nature, nor by the Law of Moſes, nor yet by the Law of Chriſt;</hi> and his whole diſcourſe was to this effect; ſo that the Appendix of his diſpute is in thoſe words; which to anſwer is enough; and truly the anſwer to them is needleſs, if we lived in an Age where Wiſdom is to be found. For what man of any reaſonable underſtanding, but muſt needs ſee that this Arrow is ſhot at the heart of the Scriptures, as well as the Sabbath: the whole Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament being as well denied to be a Rule of Life to the Gentiles, as the fourth Commandment: for all men know, that as many as ever the Old Teſtament was given to, the Sabbath was given to: and he all along throughout the whole diſpute, made it his buſineſs to deny the Sabbath was ever given to any People, or the obſervation thereof required at their hands, ſave the Stock of Iſrael, and thoſe that Proſelyted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and came and lived in the Confines of <hi>Paleſtina;</hi> and it was no ſlip of the tongue, nor an Arrow ſhot at a venture, but his mind and intention to exclude all the Scriptures that ever were written to the <hi>Jews,</hi> from being any Law or Rule of Life to us Gentiles, is manifeſt, in that he denied the Goſpel of <hi>Matthew,</hi> the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and the Epiſtle of <hi>James,</hi> only for that reaſon, becauſe they were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the Jews, and ſo concerned not us Gentiles. And his excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the Sabbath, was not that which is common to ſome others; namely, that it was of a differing nature from the other nine: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law, and therefore never given to the Gentiles. I need give no anſwer to this, having ſaid enough to this point before, in the former part of my Book: neither when I began to write, did I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to meddle with diſputes, but did think this Errour ſo ſordid, that it would die of it ſelf, and I had no pleaſure to give it a reſurrection;
<pb facs="tcp:105197:16"/>but finding the contrary, that it is as a ſpreading Lepro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> span<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there be yet ſome no wiſer than to build upon this man, as an Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> therefore I have given thee (good Reader) a true account of that Diſpute, ſo much magnified. Now for to follow theſe men with any further reply, than barely to diſcover their Errours, I cannot ſee it reaſonably to be expected, until firſt themſelves have declared what Books, or parts of Books, of the New Teſtament, they do own as a Rule of Life to bind the Conſciences of believing Gentiles, that we may know by what Texts of holy Scripture the controverſy ſhall be decided: for if we ſhould prove the Sabbath a duty from <hi>Matthew,</hi> the <hi>Acts,</hi> or <hi>James,</hi> and they, or any of them, that deny the ten Commandments, ſhould anſwer, Theſe Books were given to the Jews, and concern not the Gentiles, all our labour is loſt; but when you have called a Council, and agreed this among your ſelves, then ſhall you have a fuller Anſwer, if it be needful, and required, if I live to ſee it.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
